<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief rehersal &amp; discription, of the coronatio[n] of the hye and myghti Prince Maximilian Kyng of Romans, Boheme Hungeri &amp;c. Don at the famus citie of Francford yn the year of owr lord 1562. the month of Nouember, wyth the co[m]myng yn of the great Turcks embassater, of the presents by hym gyven, &amp; other thyngs worthy to be known.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1565</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07302</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17696</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105631</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841358</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841358</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5935</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07302)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5935)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 574:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief rehersal &amp; discription, of the coronatio[n] of the hye and myghti Prince Maximilian Kyng of Romans, Boheme Hungeri &amp;c. Don at the famus citie of Francford yn the year of owr lord 1562. the month of Nouember, wyth the co[m]myng yn of the great Turcks embassater, of the presents by hym gyven, &amp; other thyngs worthy to be known.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[G. Manilius],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Newly prented yn Gaunte :</pubPlace>
                  <date>the 27. of August M.CCCCC.LXV. [1565]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [pi]⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Maximilian --  II, --  Holy Roman Emperor, 1527-1576 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5935:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5935:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEF reherſal &amp; diſcription, of the Coronatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the hye and myghti Prince Maximilian Kyng of Romans, Bohe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me Hungeri &amp;ç. Don at the famus citie of Franc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford yn the year of owr lord 1562. the month of Nouember, wyth the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming yn of the great Turcks Emba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſſater, &amp; of the preſents by hym gyven, &amp; other thyngs wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be known.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Newli prented yn Gaunte, the 27<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of Auguſt M.CCCCC.LXV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:5935:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>YRST YT YS TO <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <lb/> noted that the cittie of Franc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ford having latitud degres 50. mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes 12. longitude, degres 25. minutes 28. ſtandeth yn that part of Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie that hyght Franconie, ſituat apon a freſh riuer wych ronneth yn to the Rhene over againſt the cittie of Mens, yn Latin Mogun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia: wythin xx. Engliſhe myle, and ys naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable betwe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wyth bargis &amp; lyghters drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by horſis, wyth ordinari &amp; dayli paſſage to and fro, wych cittie of Franckford beying Metropolitan of al Germani, and ſet yn pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce moſt indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for acces of all Princis of the Empire, from everie part, &amp; alſo for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion bothe of vyctual &amp; harbour, moſt apt &amp; propice to receyve much people, aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and recours of ſtrangiers, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monlither for the Election &amp; Coronation of their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours &amp; Kyngs ys &amp; hath ben vſed to be holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there of lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g tyme, as now yn the year of owr lord 1562. the month of Nouember, <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s accordingli, ſolemly parformed by the Kyng Maximilian inſtant Emperour, wyth ſu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p &amp; triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ph (as ys thowght) not to
<pb facs="tcp:5935:2"/>haue ben do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lyke at amy tyme, ſynce the great Charles Kyng of France, &amp; Empereur of Rome. Nor: as yt ys not poſſsible, to tel all the Royal preparation &amp; ſumptuus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion, ſo ys yt nether nedful at this tyme but only touching ſom ſpecial poyntes the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof, the gentel reader that hath not ſene, nor herd the lyke before, may refreſh hys mynd a lyttel wyth the noveltie of the matter, and content hym ſelf wythal.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Hier foloweth the Names of Dukes Marqueſſsis, Princis, Lordes, &amp; other hygh Eſtats wych came to the Caronation.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Electers or Corueſters.</head>
               <p>The buſhop of Trier. The buſhop of Cole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The buſhop of Mens. The Conte Palatin or Palſgraue. The Marques Brandenburg. The Duke of Saxon. ☆ Embaſſaters. The Duke of Aſcot for the Kyng of Spayne The Popes Emb. The Frenche Kyngs Emb The Kyng of Portingals Emb. The Kyng. of Denemarcks Em. The great Turkes Em. The Duke of Pomerans. The Venetians. The Duke of Mantua The Duke of Ferrara. ☆ Other eſtats. T<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uke of Bavier.
<pb facs="tcp:5935:3"/>The Duke of C<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ue. The Duke of Lorain. The Duke of W<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tenberg. The Duke of Makelburg. T<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ince of Orange. The Lanſgrave. The Counte Egmond. The Counte Horn. The Counte Hoghſtrate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ☆ Ladies. The Quen of Bohem, her dowgh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter &amp; 2. yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſons. The Duches of Lorain &amp; her Dowghter. The Duches of Bavier. The Duches of Saxon, wyth manny other great ladies &amp; damoſels vnknowen, and no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of Lordes, Ereles, Barons, Knyghts, Squyers and Gentilme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wych ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ther them ſelf, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them ſelf wer al known: nor yeat theyr na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, or number ys poſsible to remembe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>All wych companie of nobiliti fyrſt aſſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bled &amp; com toguyther at Frankford, abowt the 20. day of Nouember the yeare aforſayd, There abode, for the coming of Ferdinando. Emperour and Kyng Maximilian hys eldeſt ſon (whoſe Coronation we now ſpeak of) coming toguither owt of Bohemia &amp; thoſe eſt parts of Germanie. Wych beyng arived wyth yn one dayes Iournei, all the afforſayd noblemen wyth <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> traynes well apoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, &amp; mounted a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>k, yn nomber about
<pb facs="tcp:5935:3"/>5000. horſis, rood fourth of the cittie the mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning, yn good order abowt 12. Yngliſh myle to receyve the Emperour, &amp; hys ſon coming on the way from Auguſta, wych beyng then Ioyned wyth themperour &amp; hys trayn retourned toghuyther to Frankford the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me evenyng after ſon ſet, &amp; then the hoole no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber toguither was thowght to be 40000. horſis in all. And they rade al wyth dagges at theyr ſaddelbows, &amp; everi man a hearen leaſh &amp; a lyttel bugle horn about hys nek hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terlyk, and yn hys hat an oken bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che wyth faded ruſſet leaves as token of wynter. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abowt ſonſet came before yn to the cittie all their carriage wyth wago<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, carts, moyles &amp; horſis, yn great number &amp; camels 4. Wythi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 4. dayes after, was bylt vp wythin the great cathedral churche ſcaffoldes rownd abowt, ſtagies, particions &amp; ſeats, convenient and as apertayned for ſuch a cor<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nation, and from the ſayd churche to the town hawle half an Engliſh myle long the way plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked even, wyth tymber, where thes princis ſhold paſſafoot after the coronatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to dyner The Turck wyth hys company yn rych &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:5935:4"/>ſayr apparel, had got aſtandyng yn a corner howſ to ſe the paſſsing of thys po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe, on who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was more gaſyng of people, then was apon Emperour, Kyng or any thyng elſbeſyde. Affter the ceremonies of coronation, wyth long &amp; ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maſſſong, about 3. aclock at after none, themperour wyth hys ſon on the left ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; both having riche &amp; precius crownes apo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their heds, and robes of crimoſin furred wyth ermines, came fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the churche afoot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ked way, vnto the town pallace, where the dyner was prepared &amp; next before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the 6. Corveſters, lykewyſe apareled &amp; the reſidu of the other nobiliti eche ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yn hys degre, &amp; certayn officers wer apoynted to caſt &amp; ſtrew abrod monoy new coyned, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the people both of ſyluer &amp; gold. And yn the greateſt market place, wych was befo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re the Palace was acou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duct made, runnyng co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuali wyth wyn, both whyt &amp; red wych poor people fet away that wold &amp; ther beſide was a tymber houſ erect, wyth in the wych was a mighti great ox put on a broche, &amp; ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted hwole hed, legs, fete &amp; tayle &amp; all except the ſkyn &amp; bowels, &amp; wyth in the boddy was farced &amp; ſtuffed dyuers ſortes of other ſmal
<pb facs="tcp:5935:4"/>4. footed beaſtes, &amp; fowle of ſowndri Kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, as valow deare, hare, kyd, lam, pygg, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye, ſquyrel, ſwan, gooſe, heron, byttour, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lard, pheſant, pecok, capo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, partricg, quayle, p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wodcock, curlu, plover, ſnyt, blackbur<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thruſh, larck, &amp; ſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the greateſt fowle to the leſt, &amp; vnto the veari wren, and tytmoſe, wych after 2. dayes, and as many nyghts ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, was deuyded amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the people to yeat the ſame day of the coronatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Themperour then at dyner ſat vnder ariche cloth ofeſtat next thewaule, &amp; Kyng Maximilian ouer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt hym near the end, at the ſame table, &amp; no mo parſons but they 2. then wer ther 6. other tabels prepared wythin the ſame haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le for the ſix Corueſters, to ſyteche by hym ſelf but they ſarved yn the fyrſt courſ to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, &amp; the Kyng, &amp; the reſt of the Dukes &amp; Noblemen ſat at dyvers tables ther beſyde ſom 16. ſom 20. ſom. 24. at a table toguyther in order acording to their degreis. The Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of Saxon: lord marſhal, by enheritance, that day meſured ottes yn the market place, wyth apec<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of ſyluer. Wythin ij. dayes after came the Turks Embaſſator to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perours pallace &amp; preſented hym wyth an amblyng
<pb facs="tcp:5935:5"/>bay puyſtant ſtede, 4. camels furniſhed, and certain auncient Veſſel &amp; dyſhys, of purſela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; other old monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts late fownd vnder the earth, wyth in the temple of Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta Sophia yn Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinople, he roode thorowgh the ſtrets to &amp; fro, wyth 6. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions alſo an horſbak, be yn agown of cloth of gold, &amp; the other yn cry moſin vellet, and before hym a foot a 30. ſarvants &amp; ſlaves booted, and wyth ſpores a foot long fro the heale to the rowel, he hym ſelf ys a Criſten man renegat &amp; born yn Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia. Ther war alſo ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyng wyth horſis at the ryng al one day, &amp; Kyng Maximilia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, &amp; al the Dukes &amp; other Noblemen fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, affter wych tryu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ph wythin 4. dayes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perour fyrſt departed, by water to Mens, &amp; the Kyng the next day wyth hys Quene by land to Auguſta. And every, lord &amp; other Gentilman hys way, home to hys own cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tre, &amp; laſt of all the Turk, wych as he was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ducted In, wyth 40. or 50. armed men a horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bak, ſo was he lykwyſe ſafe conveyd back again, that no rude people ſhold myſvſe hym apon the way.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Sic tranſit gloria mundi.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb facs="tcp:5935:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
